Qin Chen

East China Normal University – Shanghai, 200062 \square (+86) 159 02168293 • \square chenqin_cs@163.com

Personal Profile

Qin Chen received her BS degree in 2013 and will receive her PhD degree in 2018, from the Department of Computer Science and Technology, East China Normal University. Her recent research interests include deep learning applied to Information Retrieval and Question Answering. She has publications at top conferences and journals like AAAI, SIGIR, TKDE and TIST.

Education

East China Normal University

Ph.D.

Department of Computer Science and Technology

2013-2018

Outstanding Youth Scholarship; Outstanding Graduate in Shanghai

East China Normal University

B.S.

Department of Computer Science and Technology

2009-2013

GPA: 3.61/4 (ranking: 2nd); Outstanding Graduate in East China Normal University

Academic Experience

2017.11-2018.02: International Visiting Research Trainee in the lab of Information Retrieval and Knowledge Management in York University, Canada. (Supervisor: Prof. Jimmy Huang)

o Sentence similarity modeling with collaborative and adversarial network [3]

2013.09-2017.10: Research student at the Institute of Computer Application & Shanghai Key Laboratory of Multidimensional Information Processing in East China Normal University, China. (Supervisor: Prof. Liang He & Qinmin Hu)

- o Context-aware topic modeling and hybrid retrieval [5]
- o Fine-grained time-aware retrieval [2]
- o Microblog search [12][13][14]
- o Question answering with positional attention based recurrent neural networks [4]
- o Sentence similarity modeling with context-aligned recurrent neural networks [1]

Publications

- [1] Q. Chen, Q. Hu, J. X. Huang, L. He. CA-RNN: using context-aligned recurrent neural networks for modeling sentence similarity. In AAAI, 2018, 9 pages. (Top conference in Artificial Intelligence, CCF A, accepted)
- [2] Q. Chen, Q. Hu, J.X. Huang, L. He. TAKer: fine-grained time-aware microblog search with kernel density estimation. TKDE, 2018, 14 pages. (Top journal in Database, CCF A, accepted)
- [3] Q. Chen, Q. Hu, J. X. Huang, L. He. CAN: Enhancing sentence similarity modeling with collaborative and adversarial network. In SIGIR, 2018, 10 pages. (Top conference in Information Retrieval, CCF A, accepted)
- [4] Q. Chen, Q. Hu, J. X. Huang, L. He, W. An. Enhancing recurrent neural networks with positional attention for question answering. In SIGIR, 2017, pages 993–996. (Top conference in Information Retrieval, CCF A)
- [5] **Q. Chen**, Q. Hu, J. X. Huang, L. He. Modeling queries with contextual snippets for information retrieval. TIST, 2018, 9(4): 47:1–47:26. (**Top journal, IF 3.19**)
- [6] Q. Hu, J. Zhou, Q. Chen, L. He. SNNN: promoting word sentiment and negation in neural sentiment

classification. In AAAI, 2018, 8 pages. (Top conference in Artificial Intelligence, CCF A, accepted)

[7] Q.Hu, Y.Pei, **Q.Chen**, L.He. SG++: word representation with sentiment and negation for twitter sentiment classification. In SIGIR, 2016, pages 997–1000. (**Top conference in Information Retrieval, CCF A**)

[8] W. An, Q. Chen, Y. Yang, L. He. Knowledge memory based lstm model for answer selection. In ICONIP, 2017, pages 34–42.

[9] X. Ouyang, Y. Yang, L. He, **Q. Chen**, J. Zhang. Representation learning with entity topics for knowledge graphs. In KSEM, 2017, pages 534–542.

[10] L. Chen, J. Zhou, L. He, **Q. Chen**, J. Zhang, Y. Yan. Modeling user-item profiles with neural networks for rating prediction. In ICTAI, 2017, 8 pages. (accepted)

[11] W. An, Q. Chen, W. Tao, J. Zhang, J. Yu, Y. Yang, Q. Hu, L. He, B. Li. ECNU at 2017 LiveQA track: Learning question similarity with adapted long short-term memory networks. In TREC, 2017, pages 1-9.

[12] Q. Chen, B. Wang, B. Huang, Q. Hu, L. He. ECNU at TREC 2015: Microblog track. In TREC, 2015, pages 1-6.

[13] Q. Chen, Q. Hu, Y. Pei, Y. Yang, L. He. ECNU at TREC 2014: Microblog track. In TREC, 2014, pages 1-4.

[14] **Q. Chen**, Y. Yang, Q. Hu, L. He. Locating query-oriented experts in microblog search. In SIGIR Workshop on Semantic Matching in Information Retrieval, 2014, pages 16–23.

Patents

Liang He (supervisor), **Qin Chen** et al. A method for improving social referral with user personality: China. NO. 2013102314494

Liang He (supervisor), **Qin Chen** et al. A method of multi-level query expansion in Microblogs: China. NO. 2015102944375

Liang He (supervisor), **Qin Chen**, Qinmin Hu. A method for query representation and hybrid retrieval based on context-aware topic modeling: China. NO. 2016106341742

Awards & Honors

2018: Outstanding Graduate in Shanghai, Outstanding Youth Scholarship

2017: Student Travel Grant of SIGIR'17

2015: Second Prize in National Contest of Mathematical Modeling for the Graduate Students

2014: 5th place in international microblog search competition, i.e., TREC Microblog track (5/75)

2009-2013: National Scholarship, National Encouragement Scholarship, Special Scholarship, First-Class Scholarship, Outstanding Graduate in East China Normal University

Other Professional Skills

Machine Learning

Deep Learning

Natural Language Processing

Python, Java, Matlab and C

Theano

Linux